Back in the 10th year of Yuankang
원강 10년까지만 해도
Our Xuan Kingdom's annual tax revenue
우리 선나라의 1년 세수는
Could reach over 18 million taels
1,800만 냥에 달했는데
Why, when it reached Chancellor Xie
왜 사 승상의 손에 와서는
Only 10.5 million taels remained?
1,050만 냥밖에 없죠
I
소신
Deserve death ten thousand times
죽을죄를 지었습니다
Your Majesty
폐하
After several major battles in recent years
전에 몇 차례의 큰 전쟁을 치른 후
Border trade with the Wuzhao was closed
변방과 오노의 교역이 끊겼고
This
그로 인해
Lost a large amount of revenue
수입이 크게 줄었습니다
Your Majesty
그리고 폐하께서
Implemented benevolent policies for the people
어진 정치를 베풀어
Taxes everywhere were reduced, this
각지의 세금을 감면해 주셨는데
Lost another large amount of revenue
이 또한 수입이 줄어든 이유 중 하나입니다
Your Majesty
폐하
For Your Majesty's grand ambitions
폐하의 웅대한 계획과 큰 뜻을 위해
I will definitely find a way
소신 반드시 방법을 강구하여
To quickly fill the treasury
가능한 한 빨리 국고를 불리겠습니다
Physicians often say
중병엔 극약 처방을
Severe illness requires strong medicine
써야 한다고
If there is any blame
오명이 있다면
I will bear it
제가 짊어지겠습니다
Alright, alright
됐어요 됐어
I'm tired
피곤하니
Think it over yourself
알아서 생각해 보세요
All withdraw
다들 물러가게
Yes
네
I take my leave
이만 물러가겠습니다
Come out
나오게
Your Majesty
폐하
I have verified everything
조사를 마쳤습니다
The Xie family colluded with factions
사씨 가문이 붕당들과 결탁하여
Layered exploitation of state taxes
나라의 세금을 층층이 떼어먹었습니다
Originally two hundred taels of silver
나라에서 200냥을 거둬들이면
When it reached the court
조정에 들어가는 돈은
Only one hundred taels remained
100냥밖에 되지 않아요
Also
그리고
This year's Ministry of Revenue's list of official appointments
올해 호부에서 올린 관원 임명 명단 중
More than half are Chen clan members
절반은 진씨 가문 사람이고
The remaining half
나머지 절반은
Most are also from the Xie and Zu families
사씨와 조씨
And their retainers and students
그리고 그들의 문하생이 대부분입니다
As for
그리고
The mad horse at the hunting ground
일전에 사냥터에서
That nearly collided with Your Majesty
폐하와 충돌할 뻔했던 그 말은
I
소신이
Also heard some rumors
소문을 들었는데요
Saying
말해보게
According to informants
정보원의 말에 의하면
Because the Wuzhao are skilled with horses
오노가 말을 잘 타기 때문에
So in General Zu Yue's army
조월 조 장군이
They once developed a kind of
군마를 발광하게 하는
Fierce drug that can make warhorses go mad
극약을 개발했다고 합니다
Your Majesty
폐하
Be careful
조심하셔요
And that mad horse that nearly collided with Your Majesty
그날 폐하와 충돌할 뻔한 말이
Was exactly given this drug
바로 그 약을 썼습니다
The informant also said
정보원이 말하길
That drugged horse
그 약을 흡입한 말은
Why are you beating around the bush?
빙빙 돌리지 말고
I told you to speak, so speak
얼른 말하게
That horse
그 말은 원래
Was originally meant for the second prince
둘째 전하께 주려던 건데
Only
마침
The crown prince happened to ride it
태자가 타고 갔답니다
Enough
됐네
Keep this matter buried in your stomach
이 일은 비밀로 하게
Understand?
알겠나
I understand
알겠습니다
Dismissed
물러가게
Chancellor Xie Jian'an
사건안이 승상 노릇에
Really got his money's worth
아주 살판 났군
Now
우리 아직은
We are not yet firmly established
완전히 발붙이지 못했으니
It's not yet time to move against them
그들을 건드릴 때가 아니야
I have a word of warning for you
명심해라
Don't trust and rely too much on your subordinates
문하를 너무 믿고 의지하지 말아라
Don't become their puppet
절대 그들의 꼭두각시가 되면 안 된다
You and your elder brother are family
너와 네 형이야말로 한 집 식구야
Father really had it difficult back then
부황께서도 정말 힘드셨겠어
You lamented the great families growing powerful
갈수록 몸집을 불려 가며 사사건건 방해하는
Restraining you everywhere
세가 때문에 당신은 한숨만 나옵니다.
But now
하나 나랏일에
The state still has many matters
이들의 도움이
That require these people to handle
필요한 상황이고
Yet you cannot move against them
당신은 이들을 어찌할 수 없습니다.
Now the Chen and Xie families
현재 진씨와 사씨가
Frequently intermarry
빈번한 통혼으로
If they unite
가까워진 상황이라
Will only become harder to deal with
점점 더 상대하기 어려워지는데…
Reform is necessary
반드시 개혁해야 합니다
But reform
하지만 그 개혁은
How should it be done?
어떻게 해야 할까요?
Treatise on Land
토지십론
Sheng'er's political ideas are very good
성이가 제기한 정론이 아주 좋아
Can indeed solve Xuan's current
확실히 선나라의 현재 갈등과
Contradictions and problems
문제를 해결할 수 있어
But some ideas are still too one-sided
다만 다소 단편적이라
To successfully implement it
이걸 성공적으로 시행하려면
We need someone with a high enough position
아주 높은 위치에 있으면서
And
국익을
Who can put the state's interests first
최우선으로 하는 절대적으로
And is absolutely trustworthy
신뢰할 수 있는 사람이 필요해
Marquis of Yongning
영녕후
Xie Xuan
사현